Right now,
somewhere in northern Tanzania,
a Hadza man
is napping in the shade
He's done with his work for the day
The Hadza are one of the last
hunter-gatherer groups
left on Earth,
and they still live
the way every human lived
for 300,000 years
Ancient humans worked about
2.5 hours a day
Hunting
Gathering
Cooking
Every chore
that kept them alive.
Most of us hit that before lunch.
They have never been told to
be somewhere at a specific time.
They have almost
none of the chronic diseases
that kill us.
They laugh with their families
more in one afternoon
than most of us laugh
with ours all week
And every researcher
who has lived with them
comes back saying the same thing:
They look happier than we are.
So what do they actually do all day?
In 1968,
an anthropologist named Richard Lee
published years of data
the Kung bushmen
of the Kalahari Desert
He had tracked their time
down to the minute.
His total came to about
15 hours of work per week.
Your ancestors did not have a boss
They did not pay rent
They did not have weekends,
because every day was already
mostly a weekend
So let's walk through their day
Sunrise.
You wake to the sky getting lighter,
the temperature shifting,
the camp moving around you.
You sleep on a hide
laid over flattened grass
maybe a small fire
that someone fed
during the night
Everything you own
fits in a single bag
A digging stick
Or a bow
A few hides
Maybe beads from a daughter
or a sister.
There are roughly
25 to 30 people
in your camp
You know every single one of them
You have known them
your entire life
Your grandmother sleeps
a few feet from your children.
Nobody is on a clock
The first hour is talking
A study by anthropologist Polly Wiesner
found that Bushmen spend
hours every day
in casual conversation
This is not gossip
in the trivial sense
This conversation
is the operating system
of the camp
Who is sleeping with whom?
Who took
more than their share
yesterday?
Who told a good joke
last week?
Who has been quiet
and might be sick?
This is also the entire
legal system
The way the Kung kept order
was by talking about each other
If a man hoarded meat,
people made jokes about him
until he stopped.
If a woman broke a promise,
the whispers traveled
to every camp
within a day's walk.
If you became unbearable,
eventually
no camp would have you
And that
is the harshest punishment
a hunter-gatherer can face
It almost
never had to be used
In 1969,
the anthropologist Richard Lee
saw this happen to himself
He had been living with the Kung
for years
When Christmas came,
he wanted to do
something nice for them
So he bought the biggest,
fattest ox
he could find
and brought it to camp
The Kung made fun of the gift
for weeks.
They told Lee
the ox was too skinny,
the meat would be terrible,
and he had wasted everyone's time.
Lee was confused.
He had checked the ox carefully.
It was a great animal.
So he finally asked
an old man what was going on.
The old man explained:
When a Kung hunter
brings home a big kill,
the camp doesn't celebrate.
They mock it.
They say the kill is small
the meat is bad.
The bigger the kill,
the harder they mock.
That is how the Kung
keep their hunters
from thinking they are
better than everyone else.
They had been doing
the same thing to Lee.
He had brought a great gift,
so they had to
cut him down to size.
In a Kung camp,
no one is allowed to feel
above anyone else.
Every joke,
every complaint,
every whispered story
is a tiny tool
for keeping people equal.
We built prisons.
They handled things by
talking to each other.
Mid-morning.
The men start to gather
for the hunt.
Hunting is dramatic.
It is also unreliable.
Frank Marlow,
who studied the Hadza
for decades,
found that on
any given day,
most hunters come home
empty-handed.
A successful kill happens
maybe once every few days,
sometimes less.
A Hadza hunter might
walk 20 miles in a day,
track a wounded
animal for hours,
lose it,
and come home with
nothing but a few small birds
and a sore back.
But,
when they do connect,
they connect hard.
Their arrows are tipped with
poison from the sap
of a desert rose.
The hunter shoots,
then tracks the animal for hours
while the poison works.
They have brought down
everything from antelope
to giraffe this way.
And yet, the hunters are not
the ones who feed the camp.
The women are.
Among the Hadza, women
provide more than half
of the camp's calories.
They go out in groups of 3 to 8
every day
They climb,
dig,
and gather,
returning with steady food
that does not depend on luck.
That walk back
is where most of the camp's
gossip and decisions
actually happen.
The men feast you,
the women feed you.
The most productive gatherers
in the camp
are usually the grandmothers.
Women in their 50s and 60s
bring back more food per day
than mothers in their 20s.
Many of them are still
walking five to 10 miles
into their 70s.
Anthropologists call this
the grandmother hypothesis.
It explains why humans
are the only primate species
whose women live for
decades past menopause.
The idea is that
grandmothers feeding their grandchildren
made the whole species more successful.
The children come with them.
A Hadza three-year-old
plays with a small digging stick
next to her mother, who is
digging up the day's food.
By six, she can find food on her own.
By 10, she is contributing
meaningfully to the family.
By eight, a Hadza boy can be
sent out alone with his bow
and come back with a bird.
That is just
what an eight-year-old does.
Anthropologist David Lancy
studied dozens
of traditional communities
and found that children spent
most of their day
in mixed-age play groups.
Older kids
taught younger kids.
Adults
rarely interfered.
A child who fell down
was usually picked up
by another child.
A child who asked a question
was usually answered
by a sibling.
This is how
human children learned
for hundreds
of thousands of years.
Through watching,
copying, and playing
at the work
the adults were doing
right next to them
this is the school
humans evolved to attend.
Midday.
The first food returns to camp.
It gets shared immediately.
Sharing is not optional.
It's a rule.
If a Hadza man
kills a large animal,
he does not own that meat.
He distributes it.
The hunter himself often
gets one of the worst cuts.
The camp gets the rest.
Anthropologists think
this constant sharing
is one of the things
that built the human brain.
Tracking who gave what to whom
who skipped a turn,
who stepped up when it mattered.
That is a level of social arithmetic
no other species has ever needed.
Generosity is the savings account.
Afternoon.
After eating, the camp slows.
The middle of the day is hot.
Nobody works through the heat.
People nap,
sit in shade,
repair arrows,
weave grass into baskets,
pick lice from each other's hair,
which sounds gross but takes an hour
and is mostly an excuse
to be physically close
to people you love.
The middle of the day
is for the body.
If you have to relieve yourself,
you walk a short distance
into the bush.
There is no toilet paper.
There are leaves,
sand,
water.
You don't think much about it.
If you are a woman
and you are bleeding,
you use soft grass
or moss.
Some groups
isolate menstruating women.
The Hadza do not.
You go about your day.
If you want to have sex,
you have sex.
Hunter-gatherer cultures
don't pile shame on top of it.
There is privacy when people want it
but not the heavy taboo we attach to it.
And yes,
conflicts do happen sometimes.
These people are human,
not saints.
Affairs,
jealousy,
stolen tools,
grudges that flare up.
But the way conflicts
ended was different.
In a culture where you
can pack everything you own
in 15 minutes
and walk to the next camp,
most disputes ended by
one party simply leaving.
The Bushmen called this
"voting with your feet"
If you couldn't stand someone,
you went somewhere else
for a few weeks.
By the time you came back,
the heat had passed.
Most of us cannot do that
with a mortgage and a job.
Late afternoon.
The pace picks up again.
People visit other camps,
a few miles walk to see relatives
trade gossip,
maybe a range of marriage.
The same handful of camps
stay connected this way,
year after year,
generation after generation.
By adulthood,
you know more than a hundred
people personally.
Every one of them
by name and full history.
The hunters return.
Some days they have a kill,
most days they don't.
The women who gathered all day
quietly become the day's heroes
whenever the hunters
come back empty-handed,
which is most of the time.
Evening.
Cooking begins.
roasting roots in coals,
boiling meat
in pouches with hot stones.
splitting fruit,
chewing seeds soft for the children.
Then comes the meal,
the whole camp.
Everyone.
They have done this together
every night for 300,000 years.
This is not paradise.
They get sick,
bury children,
lose people they love,
they fight and grieve
like anyone else.
But there is a kind of
suffering they do not seem to know.
The slow modern ache
of working at a job
we don't believe in
to pay for a life
that never quite arrives.
Lying awake,
comparing ourselves
to strangers
we suspect
are happier than we are.
In the late 1960s,
an anthropologist
looking at all this evidence,
called early humans
the original affluent society.
He didn't mean they had wealth.
They had almost nothing.
He meant they had time.
We made trades,
real ones.
We got vaccines,
antibiotics
and refrigeration
and indoor plumbing.
We got much longer lives.
We got fewer children
dying before they turned 5,
which in a hunter-gatherer camp
used to happen to roughly
4 out of every 10.
We got real wins.
Nobody is suggesting we go back.
But we also made
trades we don't talk about.
We invented agriculture.
We invented work
that someone else owns.
We invented bosses,
and bills
You inherited their bodies
The same nervous systems
The same need for sun,
sleep,
touch,
conversation,
and time spent doing
genuinely nothing.
We are still hunter-gatherers.
We just stopped doing it.